<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tei:elementSpec ident="tempo" module="mpm.core" mode="add" ns="http://www.cemfi.de/mpm/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <tei:gloss>tempo</tei:gloss>
    
    <tei:desc>A tempo instruction</tei:desc>
    
    <tei:classes>
        <tei:memberOf key="att.time.symbolic.date"/>
        <tei:memberOf key="att.transition.to"/>
        <tei:memberOf key="att.id"/>
    </tei:classes>
    
    <tei:content>
        <tei:empty/>
    </tei:content>
    
    <tei:attList>
        <tei:attDef ident="bpm" usage="req">
            <tei:gloss>beats per minute</tei:gloss>
            <tei:desc>The initial tempo of this instruction.</tei:desc>
            <tei:datatype>
                <tei:dataRef name="string"/>
            </tei:datatype>
            <tei:remarks>
                <tei:p>The value can be purely numeric and will be interpreted as the number of beats per minute. Alternatively, the value can also be literal and, thus, refer to a <tei:gi>tempoDef</tei:gi> in the underlying tempo style definition.</tei:p>
            </tei:remarks>
        </tei:attDef>
        
        <tei:attDef ident="beatLength" usage="req">
            <tei:gloss>beat length</tei:gloss>
            <tei:desc>The length of one beat in musical terms, e.g. quarter note=0.25, half note=0.5 etc. Without this, the tempi in beats per minute cannot be interpreted.</tei:desc>
            <tei:datatype>
                <tei:dataRef name="double">
                    <tei:dataFacet name="minExclusive" value="0.0"/>
                </tei:dataRef>
            </tei:datatype>
        </tei:attDef>
        
        <tei:attDef ident="meanTempoAt" usage="opt">
            <tei:gloss>relative position of the mean tempo</tei:gloss>
            <tei:desc>If attribute <tei:att>transition.to</tei:att> is specified and, thus, the element describes a continuous tempo transition (accel., rit.) the shape of the transition can be further refined by this attribute. Its value in the interval [0.0; 1.0] indicates the realtive position (symbolic time) between start and end of the tempo transition at which half of the tempo change is achieved, i.e. the mean tempo is reached.</tei:desc>
            <tei:datatype>
                <tei:dataRef name="double">
                    <tei:dataFacet name="minInclusive" value="0.0"/>
                    <tei:dataFacet name="maxInclusive" value="1.0"/>
                </tei:dataRef>
            </tei:datatype>
            <tei:remarks>
                <tei:p>If this attribute is not specified, the default value is 0.5, i.e. right in the middle between the <tei:att>date</tei:att> of this instruction and its end at the <tei:att>date</tei:att> of the subsequent tempo instruction.</tei:p>
            </tei:remarks>
        </tei:attDef>
    </tei:attList>
    
    <tei:exemplum>
        <tei:p>A constant tempo instruction with a numeric bpm value, a constant tempo instruction with a literal tempo value (requires an according <tei:gi>tempoDef</tei:gi>), a ritardando instruction, and an accelerando instruction. The first three have a beat length of a quarter note (1/4 = 0.25), the fourth is an eighth note (1/8 = 0.125).</tei:p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <tempo date="0.0" bpm="110.0" beatLength="0.25"/>
            <tempo date="14400.0" bpm="Vivace" beatLength="0.25"/>
            <tempo date="286500.0" bpm="Vivace" transition.to="Grave" beatLength="0.25" meanTempoAt="0.8"/>
            <tempo date="447500.0" bpm="Grave" transition.to="125.0" beatLength="0.125" meanTempoAt="0.4"/>
        </egXML>
    </tei:exemplum>
    
    <tei:remarks>
        <tei:p>The tempo instruction starts at the specified <tei:att>date</tei:att> and ends at the <tei:att>date</tei:att> of the subsequent tempo instruction. Within this time interval the tempo is either constant, monotonically increasing or monotonically decreasing. Non-monotonic shapes (e.g. acccel. followed by rit.) are composed of a sequence of multiple <tei:gi>tempo</tei:gi> elements.</tei:p>
    </tei:remarks>
    
    <tei:remarks>
        <tei:p>When using literal tempo values (in attributes <tei:att>bpm</tei:att> and <tei:att>transition.to</tei:att>) make sure that the according tempo style is associated. This is done by placing a <tei:gi>style</tei:gi> element in the tempo map before the first use of literal tempo values.</tei:p>        
    </tei:remarks>
</tei:elementSpec>
